Finding Aid for the William Beard Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
William Beard Papers
Undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0037
.84 linear feet
Biography of William Beard
William Beard (1873-1950) was a soldier, journalist, war correspondent, naval historian and long-time officer of the Tennessee Historical Commission and member of the Tennessee Historical Society. William Beard was born on July 12 1873 at Estill Springs, Tennessee, son of Captain Richard and Maria L. Dromgoole Beard of Murfreesboro, Tennessee. He enrolled June 25, 1898 with the United States Volunteers (U.S.V) and served as Quartermaster Sergeant 4th Tennessee, U.S.V. to November 1, 1898. William Beard married, Ada Scott Rice on June 9, 1909. In 1943 he became an accredited navy War Correspondent.
Scope and Content Note
The paper contain two scrapbooks, one limited to only clippings, the other scrapbook has newspaper clippings, photographs, letters, pamphlets, booklets, itineraries, newsletters, Navy Day event-related papers, bulletins, a poem, and a resume. Also included is a publication titled: “Men Make the Navy,” a series of 20 articles.
- “Men Make the Navy”, October 1, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook (clippings only) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook (clippings, photographs, letters, pamphlets, booklets, itineraries, newsletters, Navy Day event-related papers, bulletins, one poem, one resume) (Box 2)
- 1/34 – two copies of Banner Correspondent William E. Beard’s naval stories (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 2/34 – letter to William E. Beard from Chief of Naval Operations Lieutenant Commander Kernise January 24, 1946; letter to William E. Beard from Commander in Chief, U.S. Pacific Fleet and Pacific Ocean Areas J.T. Bullen, Jr. February 16, 1946; Clipping by Beard: “‘Vigorous Offense is Best Defense,’ Carrier Crew Told” January 19, 1944; journal entry “Aircraft Carrier” by William E. Beard (Box 2, Folder 2)
- 3/34 – Naval Air Transports Service Atlantic Wing, Passenger Information pamphlet; journal entry “Christmas” by William E. Beard; Press Release February 25, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- 4/34 – broken up newspaper clippings; photographs; “Commentary on Future Military Air Transport Needs and Methods of Meeting Them” (Box 2, Folder 4)
- 5/34 – newspaper clipping, titled: “Story of the Gallant, USS Tennessee” December 11, 1945; Officer’s Memorandum, No. 36S-45; Press Release “Summary of the History of the Atomic Bomb” by Lieutenant Colonel John E. Vance; Press Release: “To the Correspondents on the Appalachians”; newspaper clippings, titled: “Battered LST With 327 Aboard Docks at Norfolk Minus Stern”, Aug. 27, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- 6/34 – newspaper page 1 & 2 “Cruiser Nashville Made Gallant Record in Both Atlantic and Pacific Nashville and Murfreesboro Are Very Proud of Mrs. Douglas MacArthur” by William E. Beard August 10, 1945; Review by William E. Beard of “Empire and the Sea” by Fletcher Pratt; newspaper clipping (undated); newspaper clipping June 6, 1945 “Philippine War Thriller” edited by Mary Stahlman Douglas; photograph; letter from U.S. Navy admiral E.J. King July 5, 1944; newspaper clipping “A Grave in Khartum” by William E. Beard October 9, 1939; newspaper clipping “They’ll Not Forget ‘The Baby’ Destroyer Japs Couldn’t Sink” by Harold E. Jervey March 2, 1947; newspaper clipping “Frank Knox” by Robert R. Mullen January 18, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- 7/34 – newspaper clipping (unknown date, author, title); partial letter; Press Release September 21, 1944; newspaper clipping “Record of ‘D-Minus-Three’ Parallels History of War” July 15, 1945; Press Release June 25, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- 8/34 – newspaper clipping “Text of Japan’s Note on Panay” December 15, 1937; newspaper clipping “Philippines D-Day Drawing Nearer” August 11, 1944; Press Release; Itinerary February 15; “Tennessee and The Navy”; Newspaper clipping “How MacArthur and Nimitz Set Stage for Invasion” by John L. Springer July 15, 1945; letter from William E. Beard to John H. DeWitt May 6, 1946; Newspaper clipping “USS Buchanan Made 13 Lucky Number for U.S.” February 4, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- 9/34 – Newspaper clipping “Navy Oiler is Sunk in Action in Pacific” December 20, 1944; Press Release November 15, 1943; July 1, 1943; Newspaper clipping “JP. Morgan’s Yacht, Corsair Did Wonders During War” September 2, 1945; Newspaper clipping “‘Fighting Ike’ Home After Storm War Role” November 21, 1945; Pamphlet “Sea Power and Peace: United States Naval Institute Proceedings” by Commodore Ernest M. Eller; Naval Application; Newspaper clipping “USS Ingraham Survives Direct Suicide Blow” July 2, 1945 & “Destroyer Bryant Pacific Battle Damage Repaired” October 28, 1945; Newspaper clipping “Two Carolina Men Killed on Bower” August 31, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- 10/34 – poem by William S. Warford “The Sailor’s Twenty-Third Psalm”; Newspaper clipping “Six Jap Suicide Flyers Foiled by Ship Gunners” August 23, 1945; Newspaper clipping “Ramsay, Sea Chief of Allies, is Killed” by the Associated Press January 3, 1945; Newspaper clipping “Sea Queens’ Play Big Part In the War” by Kirke L. Simpson May 19, 1945; Newspaper clipping “Queen of Merchant Marine Plays Important Role in War” June 10, 1945 & “Victory Ship Named for Clarksville” October 13, 1944; Newspaper clipping “Admiral King, 64 Today, Faces Tremendous 7-Ocean Task” November 23, 1942; Review by William E. Beard of “Silversides” by Robert Trumbull August 15, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- 11/34 – letter to William E. Beard from Chief of Naval Operations Lieutenant Commander Kernise January 24, 1946 (first copy found in Folder 2); letter to William E. Beard from Commander in Chief, U.S. Pacific Fleet and Pacific Ocean Areas J.T. Bullen Jr. February 15, 1946 (first copy found in Folder 2); letter to William E. Beard from Chief of Naval Operations S.E. Brogan July 14, 1947; journal entry “Iowa” by William E. Beard; particle copy of journal entry “Iowa” by William E. Beard (Box 2, Folder 11)
- 12/34 – written copy of a broadcast by William E. Beard; Press Release via Western Union by William E. Beard; Letter from Douglas MacArthur to Governor Jim McCord February 23, 1946; journal entry “Roosevelt Club” by William E. Beard (Box 2, Folder 12)
- 13/34 – “Some Naval ‘Big Shots’” by William E. Beard; Newspaper clipping “38 Tennesseans Aboard Macon, Beard Reveals” by William E. Beard 1947; Newspaper clipping “Saipan, Restored From Rubble, Finest Advance Base in Pacific” September 21, 1945; Newspaper clipping of review by William E. Beard for “Woman’s Aid Turned Tide of Civil War” by Noble Hosllister July 30, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- 14/34 – “U.S.S. Bataan”; letter “U.S.S. Bataan” to William E. Beard from Lieutenant J.R. Ward January 27, 1944; Press Release “Establishment of U.S. Naval Academy Climaxed Long Struggle” (Box 2, Folder 14)
- 15/34 – Newsletter Vol. 1 No. 1 “Bataan Speaking”; letter to William E. Beard from Leland P. Lovette March 22, 1944; Press Release April 20, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- 16/34 – handwritten letter to William E. Beard from Lieutenant Jim Ward June 2, 1944; letter to William E. Beard from Val H. Schaeffer July 27, 1944; handwritten letter to William E. Beard from Fred Lawler September 20, 1944; letter to William E. Beard from Lieutenant Jim Ward November 16, 1944; journal entry “Fleet Passage” by William E. Beard (Box 2, Folder 16)
- 17/34 – journal entry “Bataan” by William E. Beard October 12; journal entry “Friday Bataan” by William E. Beard (Box 2, Folder 17)
- 18/34 – Press Release; letter February 14,1946; letter February 21, 1946; Press Release “Well Done”; Press Release; Navy graduation itinerary July 6, 1947; Newspaper clipping “Commemorating the Maine” February 15, 1948; journal entry “Bataan” by William E. Beard (Box 2, Folder 18)
- 19/34 – impartial journal entry (untitled); journal entry (blurry); Press Release August 27, 1945; journal entry “The Ranger” (Box 2, Folder 19)
- 20/34 – Press Release October 26, 1944; Press Release May 19, 1945; Press Release January 27, 1945; Press Release October 26, 1944 (copy) (Box 2, Folder 20)
- 21/34 – Press Release September 5, 1945; Press Release October 26, 1944; biography “Rear Admiral John Reginald Beardall, USN”; Newspaper clipping “Third Fleet Welcomed to West Coast” October 16, 1945; letter to Vice Admiral A.S; Carpender, USN from William E. Beard August 15, 1945; letter to commodore from A.A. Allen September 6, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- 22/34 - journal entry (undated & untitled); journal entry “Corregidor” by William E. Beard (Box 2, Folder 22)
- 23/34 – Newspaper clipping March 26, Newspaper clipping “Truman Text: ‘Victory Must be won and Kept Won’” August 10, 1945; Navy newspaper “The Macon Time” November 29, 1946; copy of “Address by Secretary of the Navy James Forrestal before The Economic Club of New York” February 25, 1947; Newspaper clipping “Winston Churchill – A Glimpse from the ‘Visitor’s Gallery’” by William E. Beard May 15, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- 24/34 – newsletter “USS Oregon City” provided for NROTC Midsummer Cruise July 21, 1947; Press Release June 25, 1946; newsletter “Know Your Navy” June 1948; journal entry “Our Nation: Dead in a Foreign Land”; journal entry/writings (Box 2, Folder 24)
- 25/34 - journal entry “Port Hudson Memories”; journal entry “Appendix Port Hudson Memories” March 23, 1863; letter/newsletter to members of the Navy League of the United States April 1, 1948; journal entry “The Explosion of the Powder-Boat” (Box 2, Folder 25)
- 26/34 - journal entry “Remembering the Maine” by William E. Beard; Speech “Ten Minute Navy Day Speech” (Box 2, Folder 26)
- 27/34 - journal entry “Some Naval Aspects of Polk’s Administration”; partial copy of journal entry “Some Naval Aspects of Polk’s Administration” (Box 2, Folder 27)
- 28/34 – newsletter “Memorial Services: Navy Day Sunday”; letter from Jim Ward to William E. Beard August 3, 1945; newspaper page “Beard Returns from Cruise; ‘Piped Over Side’ of Macon” by William E. Beard February 10, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- 29/34 – letter from Jim Ward to William E. Beard August 3; United States Memorandum from Senator Cordell Hull; letter from Major General to Senator Hull January 22, 1932; letter to William E. Beard from C.G. Abbot February 9, 1932; letter from J.R. Hildebrand to William E. Beard February 23, 1932; letter from H. [ ? ] to Senator Hull February 10, 1932; Navy newspaper “The Macon Time” February 8, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- 30/34 letter from Merrill Moore to William E. Beard; biography of Vice Admiral Frederick Carl Sherman, USN September 10, 1945; Resume of Captain M. E. Curts; letter from Merrill Moore to William E. Beard December 1943 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- 31/34 – List of ships for Navy Day Ceremony; Naval Reserve Bulletin Vol. 2 No. 2 February 1948; Newspaper clipping “General Marshall’s Speech Before Forum in N.Y.” October 30, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- 32/34 – Public Information #041356 First Carrier Task Force; History of the USS Bataan; “family” letter October 4, 1945; letter from Fred Lawler to William E. Beard October 5, 1945; biography of Captain Ward C. Gilbert U.S. Navy; Radio Distress Call transcript; photograph (Box 2, Folder 32)
- 33/34 – caricature “In Salute Magazine”; letter to editor on New York Sun May 12, 1919; letter from Geo F.A. Walker to William E. Beard July 8, 1948; journal entry “Perry” by William E. Beard (Box 2, Folder 33)
- 34/34 – Press Release July 10, 1948; booklet pertaining to the history, growth, daily routines and activities of the United States Naval Academy 1845-1945; Newspaper clipping “Antarctican”; Newspaper clipping “With Perry in Japan”; Newspaper clipping “Hollins of the Ontario” by William E. Beard (Box 2, Folder 34)